<appendix id="Background-appendix">
<title id="Background-appendix-title">Background</title>
<highlights id="Background-appendix-high"><para>This appendix begins
by providing a general overview of model compilers (sometimes
referred to as the <emphasis>software architecture</emphasis>)
followed by a brief description of the major components of &escher;.
Next, a more detailed look is taken at the two types of tasks found
in the &escher; architecture and how they interact.  Finally, the
general operational nature of each task type is described. The intent
is to provide the reader with a complete, high level view of the
&escher; architecture, sufficient to provide a context for the rest
of this manual.</para></highlights>

<section>
  <title>Model Compilers (Software Architectures)</title>
  <highlights><para>This section provides a general overview of how
  model compilers fit into the &sm; method.</para></highlights>
  
  <section>
    <title>&sm; Development</title>
    <para>The &sm; approach to software development begins by
    partitioning the system into separate subject matters referred to
    as domains.  Each domain is then analyzed using xtUML modeling
    and finally the system is implemented by translating
    the xtUML models into the chosen implementation technology (e.g.
    language, operating system, custom hardware) using the model
    compiler.</para>
    
    <para>The software architecture is that domain which deals with the
    subject matter of designing and implementing the system.  It
    abstracts the design and implementation patterns appropriate for
    the system and defines mapping rules between the xtUML models and
    these design and implementation patterns.  This approach provides a
    uniform set of data, function, and control abstractions that are
    used system wide and forms the basis for translating the xtUML models
    based on an automation of the mapping rules.</para>
    
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Software Architecture Components</title>
    <para>A software architecture is made up of three main components:
    mechanisms, rule files (formerly archetypes) and marks.
    In addition, build and
    diagnostic components are provided to facilitate constructing and
    debugging the system.  These components are described in the
    following subsections.</para>
    
    <section>
      <title>Mechanisms</title>
      <para>A mechanism is architecture functionality that is specified,
      designed, coded, and compiled to work with all xtUML models.  It is
      not customized on an xtUML element boundary.  Examples of mechanisms
      in an object-oriented ANSI C model compiler include code for 
      managing circular queues and modules written to perform set
      manipulation in a generic fashion.</para>
      
      <para>In some architectures, pre-compiled mechanisms are not
      necessary.  All code is generated from rule files or included
      in uncompiled source form.  This is true of &escher;.</para>

      <para>&escher; is purely ANSI C and generates code that can be
      compiled by any compiler compliant with the ANSI standard.  The
      core model compiler now uses no libraries or system functions at
      all.  Generated code is pure native C.  All string manipulation
      library functions (memcpy, strcpy, strcat and related) used in
      previous versions have been eliminated.  Native C functions have
      replaced these system calls.  This has been accomplished in such
      a way that a user can redefine the functions with a small
      rule file change or macro definition.</para>

      <para>This change makes it simpler and easier to integrate with
      compilers of various makes and models and manufacturers.  In
      addition, some simpler compilers will link in an entire library
      of system functions when any single function is accessed from
      the library.  Only <filename>stdio.h</filename> remains as
      exposure on this front.</para>

      <para><filename>stdio.h</filename> is included simply for convenience
      during debug (for <command>printf</command>, etc).  All generated
      code is simple, native C.  When integrating realized external
      entities and timer services (TIM), other system libraries will
      be necessary.  However, the core xtUML generated code remains
      simple ANSI C.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Rule Files (a.k.a. archetypes, templates)</title>
      <para>A rule file is a combination of an implementation pattern
      and translation rules for filling out that pattern based upon
      specifics of the xtUML models.  Thus a rule file is designed to be
      customized on an xtUML element boundary.  An example of a rule file
      in an object-oriented ANSI C model compiler is the code pattern for
      a struct that will be used to represent xtUML classes along with the
      translation rules for populating that code pattern with such xtUML
      elements as object name, attribute name, and valid events for that
      object.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Marks</title>
      <para>When there is more than one software architecture element
      into which an xtUML element can be translated,
      <emphasis>marks</emphasis> (formerly "colors") are used to
      indicate which translation
      to make.  The name ``mark'' comes from the visualization of using
      a highlighter pen to mark each element that has a particular
      property. Marks are used to direct the translation to select one
      of two or more branches in the translation rules.  It is through
      marking that design decisions are injected during the translation
      process.</para>
      
      <para>An example of the type of design information that is
      specified through marking is the mapping of analysis data types
      into implementation (e.g., C) data types.  Clearly, this is
      information that does not belong in either the xtUML models or the
      model compiler itself.  Such information is maintained
      outside the model compiler and models in marking tables that are
      accessed during the translation process.</para>
    </section>
    
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Additional Components</title>
    <para>In addition to the three basic components of a model
    compiler, the mechanisms, rule files, and marks, there are also
    two tools which come with an architecture to facilitate the
    translating and building of the system and provide some diagnostic
    capabilities for debugging the system.  These are:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>build tools</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>diagnostic tools</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Model Compiler Analogy</title>
    <para>Just as assembly language is translated into machine code,
    and a high level language is translated into assembly code (which
    is then translated into machine code), the xtUML models and their
    translation into a high level language can be viewed as the next
    evolutionary step in language development.  The xtUML models now
    become the new ``programming language'' and the software architecture
    the new ``compiler''. This approach is referred to as model based
    translative development (MBTD).</para>
    
    <para>Applying this analogy to the model compiler components,
    the mechanisms represent the run-time library that comes with a
    conventional compiler to provide the functions necessary to
    successfully execute the compiled code in the chosen
    implementation environment.  Likewise, the rule files represent the
    translation program or compiler that actually translates the high
    level source code input to assembly code output.</para>
    
    <para>
    <xref linkend="model-compiler-figure"/>
    shows an overview of how the model compilation process works in the
    context of the &bp; tool set.  The xtUML models are read from the
    repository of the &bpmb; and the translation rule files are
    fed into the &bpgen;.</para>
    
    <figure id="model-compiler-figure" float="1">
    <title id="model-compiler-figure-title">
    Model Compiler Analogy with &bp; Tool Set</title>
    <mediaobject><imageobject>
    <imagedata format="&graphicformat;" fileref="mcanalog.&graphicformat;"/>
    </imageobject></mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
  </section>
</section>

<section>
  <title>Components</title>
  <highlights><para>This section provides a brief overview of the
  &escher; architecture components by describing the Mechanisms,
  Archetypes, Marks, Build Tools, and Diagnostic Tools that make up
  the product.</para></highlights>
  
  <section>
    <title>Mechanisms</title>
    <para>The mechanisms for &escher; are implemented as ANSI C
    source code.  This code compiles at build time to provide
    support for:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>collections</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>xtUML timer interfaces</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Archetypes</title>
    <para>The &bp; translation approach employs two different types of
    rule files, <emphasis>structural rule files</emphasis> and
    <emphasis>fragment generation</emphasis> rule files.  Structural
    rule files produce the structure of the system (e.g. structure
    definitions, function definitions, state transition tables, etc.).
    Fragment generation rule files are used during the translation of
    the action language modeling the processing of the system.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Marks</title>
    <para>&escher; provides the capability to direct the translation of
    the xtUML models by marking them to:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>register xtUML and non-xtUML
      domains,</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>identify external entities as either xtUML or non-xtUML
      domains,</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>identify bridge objects for use by non-xtUML
      domains,</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>assign domain and system wide data type
      precisions,</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>tag initialization objects and objects to be
      excluded from translation,</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>establish limits to the extents of instance
      collections,</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    A detailed description of these capabilities is provided in
    <xref linkend="Marking-chapter"/>
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Build Tools</title>
    <para>&escher; is shipped with a set of build tools implemented in
    the Eclipse IDE used to translate models and compile and
    link the resulting code.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Capabilities</title>
    <para>After an application has been specified with &sm;
    xtUML models, &escher; provides the capability to translate those
    models into ANSI C source code.  This source can be compiled, linked
    and located to produce an executable load image.  This executable
    can be run on various targets.  It can be converted into an
    Intel Hex format file or Motorola S-record format file for
    loading into an EPROM or flash memory.</para>
  </section>

</section>
  
</appendix>
