<chapter id="Features-chapter">
<title id="Features-chapter-title">Features and Components</title>
<highlights id="Features-chapter-high"><para>This chapter
provides a concise overview of many of the capabilities built
into &escher;.  The basic gist of translation strategy for model
components is given in an outline format.</para></highlights>

<section>
  <title>Features</title>
  <para>&escher; delivers translation technology and a set of features
  and components found in no other model compiler existing to date.  
  The mix of optimizations, conveniences and simplicity provide a
  solid foundation upon which ``down on the iron'' embedded designs
  can be based.</para>

  <section>
    <title>&escher; Binary and Source Versions</title>
    <para>The &escher; &mc; is available in two forms: source and binary.  
    As its name implies, the source version contains the full source code for 
    the &mc; with rights for the user to modify it to suit their 
    needs.  The binary version contains full code generation capability, but 
    does not contain the &mc; source code.  This is manifest in the presence,
    or not, of the <filename>arc</filename> folder in the installation.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Multi-Pass Corroborative Translation</title>
    <para>The translation engine embodied in the &escher; &mc; performs
    two passes across the xtUML model under translation.  The first pass
    analyzes the model structure and action language semantics of each
    component.  The results of this analysis drive the generation in the
    second pass.  The second pass generates code and data that is
    minimized and optimized for speed.  Unaccessed data and unneeded
    code are eliminated.</para>
    <para>This multi-pass intelligence spans components and allows for
    optimizations at the system level based on information collected
    and collated from all components in the system.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Multi-Tasking/Threading</title>
    <para>Preemptive multi-tasking is supported on the
    <trademark class='registered'>&nukeplus;</trademark> real-time
    operation system (RTOS) and on systems supporting POSIX threading.
    Single-task operation (with or without and RTOS) is also supported.
    Tasking supplies a rich means of providing preemptive prioritization
    among the xtUML classes running in the system.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Prioritization</title>
    <para>Preemptive task/thread prioritization is provided in
    the generated C code.  Groups of xtUML classes are mapped to
    tasks running at differing priorities.</para>
    <para>&escher; also provides for prioritization through the
    marking of events.  Higher priority xtUML threads of control
    can run without being preempted by lower priority activities.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Multi-Component Support</title>
    <para>&escher; cleanly translates large systems consisting of
    multiple xtUML and realized components.  Support is provided to
    integrate and interface to hand-craft, legacy and/or off-the-shelf
    code.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Persistence</title>
    <para>&escher; supports the marking of persistent classes.
    The instance data for classes marked as persistent is restored
    at power-up from a non-volatile storage (NVS) device.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Metrics and Reporting</title>
    <para>A set of metrics can be generated and reported each time the
    model compiler is run.  Statistics on classes, associations,
    events and first pass analysis can be produced.</para>
    <para>Metrics provided can be fed back to the analyst to provide a
    focus on recognized dangerous practices and fully illegal
    operations and accesses.  Some of the metrics relate to sizing
    and complexity.  These metrics could easily be tracked
    over the life of a project to provide quality and effort related
    measurements.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Bridge/Operation Skeleton Generation</title>
    <para>Based upon information modeled in &bpmb; &escher; automatically
    generates source code frameworks for operations and outbound bridge
    implementation.  These skeleton files will actually compile
    as generated.  The user is saved from delving into generated
    code to divine interfaces required for these boundary functions.
    Kind and helpful comments are provided to guide insertion of
    bridge and operation implementation code.</para>
    <para>Support is provided for translation of OAL in operation
    and bridge descriptions.  The same action language used for &bpmv;
    is translated into the of bodies of the operation C source
    files and the bridge skeleton files.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>``Call Outs'' for User Code</title>
    <para>Several hooks have been supplied to allow easy interfacing
    of user supplied code to the system level generated code.
    A source module is automatically generated that supplies
    empty functions which are invoked at various points during
    initialization, dispatch processing and shut down.  These
    empty functions can be populated with user code for ``can't
    happen'' events,
    hardware bring-up, ``background'' processing, legacy
    clean-up and more.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>UDT Precision and Pointer Types</title>
    <para>To allow optimization for space and control over
    precision, the storage classes of integer and real based
    user-defined
    data types (UDTs) can be supplied by the user.
    &escher; also allows user-defined data types to be
    implemented as pointers.  The pointer types are very
    convenient for passing across bridges (in both directions).
    Precision and pointer information is provided to the
    model compiler through marking.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Attribute Bit Fields</title>
    <para>Further optimization of space is provided through
    ANSI C bit field support.  Multiple attributes can be packed
    into a single word of storage.  This feature may also be
    used (with caution) in conjunction with memory mapped classes
    to model hardware with xtUML constructs.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Selection Optimization</title>
    <para>&escher; attempts to optimize <command>select
    any [inst_ref] from instances of [key_letters] where
    [where clause]</command> when the where clause
    is checking for equality of the identifier.  &escher;
    optimizes for code space.  In addition,
    hooks into the scanning routines are provided to enable
    customizations to the selection search algorithms.
    Applications dealing with large collections of class
    instance data (hundreds or thousands) may use these hooks
    to further speed the selection process.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Interrupt Handler Bridging</title>
    <para>&escher; provides a safe way to bridge into the application
    from interrupt handlers (or other external tasks).  Consistency is
    maintained in software architecture data structures and
    application data access sets.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>User Defined Archetypes</title>
    <para>A means is provided for the user to supply application
    specific fule file functions.  This capability serves to
    extend the marking capabilities of &escher;.  It is possible
    to steer code generation in such a way as to provide customizations
    characteristic of particular target platforms, compilers and
    tool sets.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>ANSI C Purity and Simplicity</title>
    <para>&escher; is purely ANSI C and generates code that can be compiled
    by any compiler compliant with the ANSI standard.  The core
    model compiler uses no libraries or system functions.
    <filename>stdio.h</filename> is included simply for convenience
    during debug (for <command>printf</command>, etc).  All generated
    code is simple, native C.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Preexisting Instances Defined in Data</title>
    <para>As of version 3.1, &escher; supports initialization of
    preexisting instances in data.  This provides a substantial
    optimization in both bring-up execution speed and overall code
    footprint.  Instead of creating, relating and initializing all
    of the classes at start-up, pre-existing class instances can be
    pre-populated with static initializers.  Support is maintained for
    dynamic initialization using an initialization function (or an
    initialization object).</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Target Code Inside Action Language</title>
    <para>&escher; allows the user to intermix target source code
    with action language.  These pieces, nicknamed
    snippets, are delimited by special strings.  Snippets are allowed 
    anywhere action language is supported: bridge operations, functions, 
    class and instance-based operations, mathematically-dependent 
    attributes, and state actions.</para>

    <para>Snippets are delimited by <literal>/*#inline</literal>
    on a line by itself, followed by the target source code, followed by
    <literal>*/</literal> on a line by itself.  C++ style comments 
    (comments preceeded with "<literal>//</literal>") are allowed inside 
    a snippet.  Here is an example:

    <programlisting>
    /*#inline
      // Don't Panic
      int a = 42;
      printf( "The answer is %d\n", a ); 
    */</programlisting></para>

    <para>While the primary use of this feature is to add target code to 
    action language, it should be noted that &escher; does not 
    restrict (or care) what is placed inside the snippet.  The key point 
    is that &escher; simply allows these inline snippets to fall through 
    the code generation process to the output target code.  No additional 
    processing of the snippet is provided.</para>

    <para>A compiler directive called <constant>XTUMLMC_INLINE</constant> 
    is used to allow conditional target compilation of the snippet code.  
    Each snippet in the generated source code starts with 
    <programlisting>#if XTUMLMC_INLINE</programlisting> 
    and ends with 
    <programlisting>#endif</programlisting>
    This directive (and, hence, snippet usage) is set active (1) by default 
    in <filename>sys_user_co.h</filename>.</para>

    <para>Note that entering target-specific code into a model can have 
    consequences. A good model represents an implementation-independent 
    specification of the application. Adding target-specific code to the model 
    can reduce this flexibility.</para>  

    <para>On the other hand, done carefully, code in models can overcome some of
    the limitations of the action language. For example, code in models can 
    allow you to access target-specific registers and ISRs, give you access to 
    unmodelled external code modules, and use target assembler code in an 
    action.</para>

    <para>In nearly all cases, properly constructed models and action language 
    can completely describe an application.  Take care when adding code to 
    models.  Understand the benefits and do not underestimate the costs.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Dynamic Memory Allocation (Or Not)</title>
    <para>By default &escher; creates applications that are very
    restrictive in their memory usage.  This is done by statically 
    allocating all memory that will be needed when the application 
    starts. Some applications, however, need the flexibility of being 
    looser in their memory consumption.  See
    <xref linkend="DynamicMemoryAllocation-section"/> for information on 
    how to allow your application to dynamically allocate additional 
    memory as needed.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>XMI Export</title>
    <para>XMI is an acronym for XML Metadata Interchange.  &bp; &escher; 
    supports the ability to export your models in XML format using XMI 2.1.  
    XMI is an Object Management Group (<ulink url="http://www.omg.org">OMG
    </ulink>) specification for the use of XML in serializing models so 
    that they can be imported, exported and interchanged.</para> 

    <para>To export your project using XMI: 

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>Open the <GUIMenuItem>Project &gt; Properties</GUIMenuItem> dialog</listitem>
      <listitem>Select <GUILabel>Builders</GUILabel></listitem>
      <listitem>Check the box next to <GUILabel>XMI 2.1 Export</GUILabel></listitem>
      <listitem>Uncheck the box next to <GUILabel>CDT Builder</GUILabel></listitem>
      <listitem>Select <GUIButton>OK</GUIButton></listitem>
      <listitem>Right-click on your project and select <GUIMenuItem>Build Project</GUIMenuItem></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>&escher; will run in a special mode that generates an XML file 
    for each of your domains.  The files will be placed in the 
    <filename>src</filename> folder of your project.  The file(s) are named 
    <filename>&lt;domain&gt;_xmi.xml</filename>.</para>

    <para>Once the export is complete, be sure to uncheck the 
    <GUILabel>XMI Export</GUILabel> builder and check the <GUILabel>CDT 
    Builder</GUILabel> to put &escher; back into normal code generation mode.
    </para> 
  </section>
</section>

<section>
  <title>Components</title>
  <para>&escher; is a modular software architecture characterized by a
  distinct effort to maximize component independence.  The coupling
  between the model compiler components has been minimized while
  maximizing component cohesion.  A model of the architecture drives the
  implementation of the generation components.</para>

  <para>To a great extent components can be modified independently.
  Additional components can be added.  This makes &escher; ideal for
  extension and modification.  In a limited fashion, individual
  architecture components can be ``unplugged'' and new or modified
  components ``plugged in'' to replace them.  For example, the strategy
  for collecting instances can be changed by modifying or replacing
  only the localized component.  Names and coding style rules are
  concentrated into a single component allowing architects to dial
  in a preferred naming convention and generation style.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Classes</title>
    <para> Each class is translated into an ANSI C structure.  Instances
    are maintained in collections of instances of classes (class
    extents).  Space for class instances is
    pre-allocated at bring-up time.</para>
    
    <section>
      <title>Creation</title>
      <para>Creation occurs in constant time.  Creation can occur
      synchronously with the create action language statement or
      asynchronously with a creation event.  In synchronous creation,
      no action is executed.  In asynchronous creation, a creation
      state is executed and at minimum initializes the instance
      identifier.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Deletion</title>
      <para>Instance deletion moves an class instance from the
      active extent and deactivates it onto a list of inactive
      (``inanimate'') class instances.  If no action language
      ever performs deletion of a particular class, no deletion
      accessor method is generated.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Selection</title>
      <para>Instance selection is optimized for speed when selecting
      based on the instance identifier.  For unoptimized selections O(N)
      (linear) time is required.  (&escher; provides
      O(N) for all ``blind selections'', <command>select any from
      instances of</command> action language commands.)
      Hooks are provided for architect replacement of certain
      signature selection search functions.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Attributes</title>
      <para> Attributes are elements of the translated structure.  Most
      attributes are translated with no function interface layer.  No
      call/return overhead is incurred for most attribute read and
      write operations.  Code is generated to directly access attribute
      data.  Speed is optimized.</para>
      <para>In typical models, some attributes are never accessed.
      &escher; detects this situation and omits the implementation of
      attribute data elements that are never accessed.  Unused data is
      optimized away.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  
  <section>
    <title>Associations</title>
    <para> Associations are optimized by storing a copy of the instance
    handle as extended attribute data.  This optimization is
    implemented between sub/super-types as well.</para>
    <para>As with data attribute elements, &escher; optimizes away
    unused referential attributes.  Relate, unrelate (link and unlink)
    and association traversal operations are optimized for low
    overhead.  These operations are performed directly on instance data
    when appropriate avoiding the generation and associated run time
    overhead of function calls.</para>
  </section>
  
  
  <section>
    <title>State Models</title>
    <para> The translated state models are optimized for speed.  State
    transitions and action dispatches execute in constant time.
    The state event matrix is implemented as a two dimensional
    array.  Rows represent states; columns are indexed by event
    to obtain the transition.</para>
    
    <section>
      <title>Actions</title>
      <para> Actions are translated into functions associated by
      name and packaging with the class containing the state model
      containing the state action.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Events</title>
      <para>Adherence to &sm; event rules is assured in the generated
      code.  Centralized event queues order events for the entire
      system.</para>
      <para>Prioritized events can be marked by the user. 256
      priority levels are provided.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Creation Events</title>
      <para> Creation events are recognized and treated differently
      from non-creation events.  The model compiler will create an
      instance of the class before the event is delivered.  The event
      will cause a transition into the creation state and execution of
      the associated action.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Final States</title>
      <para> Final state actions delete self after executing the
      specified processing.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  
  <section>
    <title>Bridges and Operations</title>
    <para> Functions (bridges) and operations are listed together, because
    &escher; treats them with a great deal of symmetry.  Functions and
    operations translate into C function invocations.  Any number of
    arguments can be passed.</para>
    
    <para>&escher; generates bridge and operation frameworks.  These
    frameworks provide the entire invocation interface.  A comment is
    provided to guide the user in where to insert implementation code.
    These skeletons will compile with or without inserted user code.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  
  <section>
    <title>Miscellaneous</title>
    <para>These are the unclassified features.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Initialization</title>
      <para> Marking allows &bpmv; flavored initialization objects
      to be used for system initialization.  In addition, several
      initialization objects can be defined in the model and
      only one marked to generate code.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Style Dials</title>
      <para> Various stylistic and implementation conventions are
      centralized and documented to be easily controlled by the software
      architect.  Generated file names, directory structure, coding
      conventions and even coding style can be dialed in by the user.
      (Look for fule files with the word ``name'' in the file name.)
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Metrics</title>
      <para>&escher; is tooled to support a measured development
      process.  As with style, metrics can be customized easily.
      &escher; gathers and reports many metrics including statistics
      quantifying classes, states models, state actions, event flavors,
      association and marking summary information.</para>
    </section>
    
  </section>
</section>


<section>
  <title>Restrictions and Limitations</title>
  <para>See release notes for most recent restrictions and limitations.
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Dynamic memory allocation is off by default.  System storage space
    for all instances is pre-allocated at start-up.  This implies
    marking the OIM to define the maximum number of instances needed
    for each class.  Note that &escher; intelligently determines
    rational defaults for instance and event populations.  Sophisticated
    analysis is performed to size instance, event and queue
    populations across multiple components.  Marking
    is used to dial these in tightly.  Dynamic memory allocation can
    be enabled with marking.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Some platforms have no real time clock.  Therefore
    date and time may not be available in standard Gregorian or Caesarian
    form.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>State machines are optimized for speed rather than
    space.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Navigations of composed associations must explicitly
    use the ``real'' (non-composed) association
    formalizations.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Association conditionality is not enforced by
    the model compiler.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>&escher; attempts to optimize <command>select
    any [inst_ref] from instances of [key_letters] where
    [where clause]</command> for code size when the where clause
    is checking for equality of the identifier.  Future versions
    of &escher; may provide advanced (hashed) searching techniques
    to optimize the blind selections for speed.  In &escher;,
    certain limitations apply to the selection
    optimization when unnecessary parentheses are used in the
    where clause expression.  To guarantee the best optimization,
    avoid unnecessary parentheses in where clauses.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Blind selections following a create and in the same
    scope as the create may not see the newly created instance in the
    extent.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><command>create object instance of</command>
    <emphasis>keyletters</emphasis> (create with no return
    value) is allowed only when the identifier of
    class <emphasis>keyletters</emphasis> is of type
    unique_ID.</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </para>
</section>
</chapter>
