<chapter id="Enum-chapter">
<title id="Enum-chapter-title">Enumerated Types</title>
<highlights id="Enum-chapter-high"><para>&bpmb; allows users
to define types derived from its set of core data types.
Support for the &bpmb; interface for defining enumerated types
is fully supported.</para></highlights>

<section>
  <title>Overview of Enumeration Support</title>
  <highlights><para>Enumerations provide the ability to represent
  discrete component sets in xtUML.  &escher; supports the translation
  of these enumerated types into ANSI C.</para></highlights>
  
  <para>Many systems require the ability to define a data type that can
  take on a finite number of discrete values.  The current release of
  &bp; provides support for enumeration data types.  &escher;
  &escherversion; provides support for the translation of enumerations
  and provides several extensions that are described here.  Previous
  versions of &bp; did not support enumerations natively within the
  tool.  The previous method for specifying enumerations by using
  strings is no longer documented but is still supported by &escher; for
  backward compatibility.  Each enumeration specified in the xtUML models
  is translated into ANSI C defined constants.</para>
</section>

<section>
  <title>Specifying Enumerations</title>
  <highlights><para>To specify an enumeration using the facilities
  provided by &escher;, use the steps described
  in the following sections.</para></highlights>

  <para>Use &bpmb; create your enumeration data types.</para>
  
  <section>
    <title>Specifying a Discrete Value for Enumerators</title>
    <para>&escher; supports the specification of a discrete value for
    each of the enumerators for an enumeration. There are two ways in
    which the value can be assigned: 1) through the use of a keyword in
    the description of the enumerator, and 2) through marking. In the
    absence of any value specified by the user, &escher; assigns a
    default.  &escher; gives priority to those values specified via
    marking.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Value Keyword</title>
      <para>&escher; recognizes a special keyword that the analyst
      places in the description of the enumerator.  The keyword can be
      any one of the following three: Value, value, or VALUE.  Note that
      the keyword is case sensitive so using vaLuE will not work
      properly. The keyword should be used on a single line as in:
      <blockquote><programlisting>
Value:  3
      </programlisting></blockquote>
      with a colon immediately after the keyword followed by the desired
      value.</para>
      <para>Other examples of usage include:
      <blockquote><programlisting>
value:  0x4
Value:  23
VALUE:  0xFFF
      </programlisting></blockquote>
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Marking</title>
      <para>The marking function
      <function>TagEnumeratorDiscreteValue</function> can also be used
      to specify the value for an enumerator.  The marking function
      overrides any value specified in the analysis model.  See <xref
      linkend="SpecifyingEnumValues-section"/> for complete
      details on this marking option.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

    
  <section>
    <title>Accessing an Enumeration from a Non-Modeled Domain</title>
    <para>Enumerations that are defined within a modeled component can
    also be used by manually written code.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Enumeration Header File Name</title>
      <para>The name of the header file containing the enumerations for
      a component is of the following form:  <filename>(registered component
      name)_enums.h</filename>.  For example, the name of the header
      file containing the enumerations defined in the microwave component
      with registered name M is <filename>M_enums.h</filename>.  The file
      is placed in the system-level include directory
      <filename>system/gen/include</filename>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Access to an Enumeration</title>
      <para>In &escher;, enumerations translate into simple
      <command>#define</command>s.  Each member (enumerator) of
      the enumeration is defined to a value.  Each enumerator
      member uses the name of the enumeration as the part of it
      own name to prevent name collisions between enumerators in
      different enumerations.</para>
      <para>To use the enumerators in a hand-coded C module,
      simply include the <filename>(component)_enums.h</filename>
      and use the desired constants defined within.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>


<section>
  <title>Using an Enumeration</title>
  <highlights><para>An enumeration can be used by the component in which
  it is defined as well as by other components.  The following sections
  describe the use of an enumeration.</para></highlights>

  <section>
    <title>Legal Uses of an Enumeration</title>
    <para>The user-defined type that represents an enumeration is a
    legal type for all of the following data items:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>object attribute</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>event supplemental data item</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>bridge argument</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>bridge return value</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>operation argument</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>operation return value</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>domain function argument</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>domain function return value</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>Enumerators
    can also be used in the following operations:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>comparison for equality and
      inequality</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>assignment to local variable</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>

</section>

</chapter>
