<chapter id="Initialization-chapter">
<title id="Initialization-chapter-title">Initialization and Preexisting Instances</title>
<highlights id="Initialization-chapter-high"><para>This chapter
explains how to initialize and start the system.  Initialization
must deal with bringing up the architecture system code as well
as initialization for preexisting instances.
</para></highlights>

<para>
&escher; supports dynamic and constant initialization of preexisting
instances.  Dynamic initialization is simple and flexible while
constant initialization is a powerful optimization allowing for
reduction in code space and increase in initializationspeed.
</para>

<section id="Initialization-chapter-Overview-section">
  <title>Initialization Overview</title>
  <highlights><para>It is possible to define preexisting instance
  populations dynamically with action language and constantly with data
  definitions.  Instance populations can be static, dynamic and/or
  read-only.</para></highlights>

  <para>&escher; supports two methods of initialization, dynamic and
  constant.  Both methods provide a means of creating and
  setting up the preexisting instances required for a system at
  bring-up time.  Both methods provide a way of creating the preexisting
  instances, relating them one to another and setting the values of
  their attributes.  Each method of initialization has advantages and
  disadvantages.  Each method is useful in design situations that
  leverage the advantages.  The following sections will describe each
  method of performing system initialization.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Preexisting Instances</title>
    <para>When specifying a system with xtUML models, the analyst is
    allowed to assume that there are preexisting instances of classes
    within the models.  &escher; provides two methods for specifying
    these preexisting instances, the values of their attributes, and
    the relationships between them.  This dynamic creation, linking
    and initialization of preexisting instances is described in
    <xref linkend="Initialization-chapter-DynamicInit-section"/>.</para>
    
    <para>The preexisting instances of xtUML classes can be
    created during system bring-up from the specifications
    provided by the analysts in
    the form of initialization functions.  These preexisting instances
    are created before normal execution of the system is allowed to
    proceed.  Thus, the xtUML models can assume that all the preexisting
    instances exist before any events are accepted.</para>
    
    <para>Note that &escher; automatically creates a single instance
    for every assigner in the system.  The analyst does not need to
    model or mark anything to make this happen.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Terminology</title>
    <para>In order to avoid confusion resulting from the following
    paragraphs as well as in future documentation,
    the following definitions will be used with respect to
    instance populations and preexisting instances:
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para><emphasis>static instance population:</emphasis>
    an instance population to which additions or
    deletions are never made during system execution (after
    initialization)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis>implicitly defined static instance
    population:</emphasis> the use of a static instance
    population for a class due to the absence of associated
    create/delete statements in model action
    language</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis>explicitly defined static instance
    population:</emphasis> the use of a static instance
    population (no creates/deletes) for a class based on a
    <function>TagStaticInstancePopulation</function> mark for that
    class</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis>dynamic instance
    population:</emphasis> an instance population to which
    additions and deletions may be made during system execution
    (after initialization)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis>implicitly defined dynamic instance
    population:</emphasis> the use of a dynamic instance
    population for a class based on the presence of associated
    create/delete statements in model action
    language</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis>preexisting instances defined using
    executable statements:</emphasis> preexisting instances that are
    established at run time through the use of an executable
    initialization routine</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis>dynamic initialization:</emphasis>
    preexisting instances that are established at run time through the
    use of an executable initialization routine (same
    as<emphasis>preexisting instances defined using executable
    statements</emphasis>)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis>preexisting instances defined in
    data:</emphasis> preexisting instances which are established
    through the use of constant data (in the form of ANSI C
    initializers)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis>constant initialization:</emphasis>
    preexisting instances which are established
    through the use of constant data (in the form of ANSI C
    initializers) (same as <emphasis>preexisting instances defined in
    data</emphasis>)</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis>read-only instance population:</emphasis>
    instance population that cannot be written</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>It is easy to see that many combinations of static/dynamic,
    read-only, implicit/explicit and preexisting can occur in normal
    system analysis.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Constructs Supported</title>
    <para>In &escher; 3.1 and beyond, preexisting instances can be
    defined in data for any normal modeling construct supported by
    &escher;  For example, dynamic or constant initialization can be
    defined for:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>simple 1-1 associations</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>simple 1-* associations</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>associatives (1-1, 1-*, *-*)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>subtypes</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>supertypes</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>sub/supertypes</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>simple reflexive associations</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>simple 1-* reflexives</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>reflexive associatives</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>asymmetric reflexive associatives</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
</section>

<section id="Initialization-chapter-DynamicInit-section">
  <title>Dynamic Initialization</title>
  <highlights><para>The simples and easiest way to initialize
  preexisting instance is using dynamic
  initialization.</para></highlights>

  <section>
    <title>Dynamic Init Process</title>
    <para>Dynamic initialization uses sequences of action language
    statements to create, relate and set attributes of preexisting
    instances.  This form of initialization has been supported by &escher;
    since the first release (1.0).</para>
    <para>Action language statements in initialization functions (or
    previously in init objects) are executed once when a system first
    starts.  The action language statements perform
    <command>create</command> statements to
    create the preexisting instances.  <command>Relate</command>
    statements execute to establish associations between these newly
    created instances.  Action languages statements are executed which
    write the attribute values of the preexisting instances.</para>
    <para>When all of the action language statements are complete for all
    init functions (tagged with
    <function>TagInitializationFunction</function>), then all preexisting
    instances are fully established and initialization is complete.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Pros and Cons of Dynamic Init</title>
    <para>Advantages to dynamic initialization include:
    <informaltable frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
    <tgroup cols="2">
    <colspec colwidth="*"/>
    <colspec colwidth="3*"/>
    <tbody>
    <row>
    <entry>flexibility</entry>
    <entry>It is easy to add, delete and/or change dynamic initialization.
    This is done by simply adding, deleting and/or changing the action
    language in the init functions.</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
    <entry>simplicity</entry>
    <entry>Dynamic initialization is simple and easy to understand.</entry>
    </row>
    </tbody>
    </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    </para>

    <para>Disadvantages to dynamic initialization include:
    <informaltable frame="none" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
    <tgroup cols="2">
    <colspec colwidth="*"/>
    <colspec colwidth="3*"/>
    <tbody>
    <row>
    <entry>memory space</entry>
    <entry>The space in the system instruction store used by the
    initialization action language statements
    can be substantial.  This space is not availabe for use after the
    init process is complete.</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
    <entry>speed</entry>
    <entry>It takes time (execution time) during bring-up to create,
    relate and populate the preexisting instances.</entry>
    </row>
    </tbody>
    </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Initialization Functions</title>
    <para>The basic building block for specifying preexisting instances
    is the initialization function.  This approach provides the user with
    the ability to use the same set of preexisting instances for
    simulation with the &bpmv; as are used during the actual execution
    of the system on the target platform.</para>
    
    <para>Initialization functions
    contain the action language that describes the set of
    preexisting instances for the subsystem or domain.
    Initialization functions are normal functions and can
    be invoked during normal system execution as well as at
    start-up.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Rules for Creating Initialization Functions</title>
    <para>The rules for constructing initialization functions are
    enumerated below.
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>Each subsystem can have one to many
      initialization functions.  The functions will be invoked
      in alphabetical order during bring-up.
      Initialization functions are identified by
      marking in the <filename>domain.mark</filename> marking
      file.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Initialization functions are tagged with
      the marking function <function>TagInitializationFunction</function>.
      </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Initialization functions can take no
      arguments.  Return values will be ignored.</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Example of Dynamic Initialization</title>
    <para><xref linkend="as2class-figure"/> shows the xtUML class diagram
    for the autosampler example model.  Note that the autosampler
    example model can be found in the <filename>examples</filename>
    directory of your &escher; installation.
    <xref linkend="as2init-figure"/>
    shows the action language statements contained in the initialization
    function for the autosampler domain.  The function is marked as
    an init function with the statement
    <programlisting>TagInitializationFunction( "setup" )</programlisting>
    in the <filename>domain.mark</filename> marking file.
    This init function executes
    creates, relates and attribute writes to establish all preexisting
    instances.  The function runs once and only once at system
    start.

    <figure id="as2class-figure" float="0" pgwide="1">
    <title id="as2class-figure-title">Autosampler Class Diagram</title>
    <mediaobject><imageobject>
    <imagedata format="&graphicformat;" fileref="as2class.&graphicformat;"/>
    </imageobject></mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <figure id="as2init-figure" float="0">
    <title id="as2init-figure-title">Autosampler Init Function</title>
    <informalexample>
    <para>
    <programlisting>
create object instance car of CAR;
car.carousel_ID=10;
car.current_position=10;
create object instance row of ROW;
relate row to car across R1;
row.radius=10;
row.current_sampling_position=0;
row.maximum_sampling_positions=20;
row.sampling_time=3000000;  // 3 seconds
row.needs_probe=false;
create object instance probe of SP;
probe.probe_ID=1;
probe.radial_position=20;
probe.theta_offset=40;
probe.current_position="up";
probe.available = true;
    </programlisting>
    </para>
    </informalexample>
    </figure>

    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Multi-Domain Dynamic Initialization</title>
    <para>In systems with more than one domain, dynamic init is only
    slightly more complex.  Initialization functions are written for
    each domain.  These multiple init functions establish the
    preexisting instances (PEIs) for the multiple domains.  The init
    functions are each marked with
    <function>TagInitializationFunction</function> in each domain's
    corresponding <filename>domain.mark</filename> marking
    file.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Multi-Domain Init Sequencing</title>
    <para>In some systems it is important that certain domains be
    initialized before other domains.  Or, there may be requirements on
    the ordering of the initialization between domains.  In these cases,
    a function in only one domain is tagged as an init function (using
    <function>TagInitializationFunction</function>).  This function
    then invokes functions in the other domains, thus imposing the
    desired order on the initialization sequence.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Initialization in Simulation</title>
    <para>To simulate the xtUML models with the same set of preexisting
    instances that are used on the target system, the analyst must
    invoke the initialization functions.  &bpmv; provides a facility
    to do this very easily.</para>
  </section>
</section>
</chapter>
