<section id="Containoids-section">
  <title>&escher; Extent Prediction and Marking</title>
    <para>First pass translation collects statistics used to
    conservatively estimate the number of container nodes (containoids)
    required by the system.</para>

    <para>There are three different uses for instance containoids:
    class extents, association extents and selection extents.
    Selection extents govern the total size of transient instance
    reference set variables in the actions.  This represents values
    in the variable type <type>inst_ref_set</type>.
    The required number of containoids for each flavor is summed
    to provide the upper limit to total containers.
    <programlisting>#define SYS_MAX_CONTAINERS \
    ( SYS_MAX_OBJECT_EXTENT + SYS_MAX_RELATIONSHIP_EXTENT + SYS_MAX_TRANSIENT_EXTENT )</programlisting></para>

    <para>SYS_MAX_OBJECT_EXTENT is a sum of all of the extent counts across
    all the domains of the system, which are sums of the class extents
    in each domain.  Each class extent is allocated to be the system
    default for class extents, a marked value of the system default
    or the marked value for the specific class.</para>

    <para>Selection extents are calculated by multiplying the largest
    number of selects that can occur in any action by the largest extent
    of any class.  Thus allowing for the worst case action to select
    the largest class extent each time.  This value is set in
    SYS_MAX_TRANSIENT_EXTENT.
    <programlisting>transient containers = ( max selects ) * ( largest class extent )</programlisting></para>

    <para>Association extents are allowed to be as big as they would
    need to be if all instances on the MANY side were always
    participating.  This value is set in SYS_MAX_RELATIONSHIP_EXTENT.
    <programlisting>association containoids = ( number of MANYs ) * ( largest class extent )</programlisting></para>

    <para>The following marks govern these extent sizes:

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><programlisting>MaxObjectExtentSize( "component", "key_letters", value )</programlisting></listitem>
      <listitem><programlisting>MaxSystemObjectDefaultExtentSize( value )</programlisting></listitem>
      <listitem><programlisting>TagMaximumRelationshipExtentSize( value )</programlisting></listitem>
      <listitem><programlisting>TagMaximumSelectionExtentSize( value )</programlisting></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    See the proper sections in the &escher; Users Guide for details
    on these marking parameters.</para>

    <para>Association extents refer to the sets of instances
    participating
    in a association with multiplicity MANY.  Sets built from
    linked lists are used to optimize traversal of associations with
    multiplicity MANY.  For example, in the following model,
    A 1---R1---* B,
    class B does not need an extent set; it simply needs a single
    pointer reference to the A instance.  The A instance however does
    need a set of instance references.  Such a set uses "containoids"
    to collect the B instances related to the A instance.
    &escher; calculates the worst case (biggest possible) association
    extent.</para>

    <para>The extent can be marked to be smaller than the worst case
    maximum using TagMaximumRelationshipExtentSize.
    <command>MarkObjectExtentSize</command> will also have an effect on
    the calculated total.</para>

    <para>If no extent size marking is supplied, &escher; will
    calculate a worst case for a model of a higher number of
    containers.  &escher; will see R1 and allow for all possible
    instances of B to participate with instances of A.  (This is the
    most important point!)</para>

    <para>Another way to understand how &escher; calculates this maximum
    is as follows:
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>Count the number of MANYs (---*) on a class
      diagram.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para> For each MANY (---*), add the maximum class
      extent on the MANY side (B above).</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>There are adjustments to be considered in the
      case of associative classes.</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    This sum across all domains in the system will be the
    SYS_MAX_RELATIONSHIP_EXTENT.</para>
</section>
