<chapter id="Collections-chapter">
<title id="Collections-chapter-title">&escher; Collections</title>
<highlights id="Collections-chapter-high"><para>Lists are used by &escher;
to keep track of collections of instances in the system.  Collections
of instances appear in several contexts including pools of instances
of classes, sets of instances participating in an association and
sets of instances resulting from SELECT MANY statements.</para></highlights>

<section>
  <title>&escher; Collections</title>
  <highlights><para>&escher; manages collections of instances using
  various collection mechanisms which are selectable through marking.
  As of version 3, &escher; provides two flavors of collection
  container, singly linked lists (slists) and doubly linked lists
  (dlists).  Each container strategy has advantages and disadvantages
  with regard to code size and speed.  In general, dlists are faster
  but take more storage.  In the following sections details of
  these constructs are outlined.</para></highlights>

<!--
<section>
  <title>Overview</title>
  <highlights><para>&escher; manages collections of instances using
  markable flavors of collection (container)
  mechanism.</para></highlights>
-->

  <section>
    <title>Containers</title>

    <para>Collections of class instances (objects) must be supported by
    any model compiler.  Processing performs operations on these
    sets of data.  Instances can be collected and organized in
    several ways.  At minimum, a model compiler must be able to
    support:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>selection from the existing instances of any
      specified class</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>selection from instances of any associated
      class</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>the analysis variable type <type>inst_ref_set</type>
      </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    We refer to the first case as instance extents.  The second are
    referred to as association extents.  The third are
    transient set variables (often called selection extents).</para>

    <para>As of version 3, &escher; maintains collections in linked
    lists.  Linked lists are flexible and relatively light
    weight (small, simple code).</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Sets</title>

    <para>Operations on sets include <function>Insert</function>,
    <function>Remove</function>, <function>Clear</function>,
    <function>Copy</function>, <function>Cardinality</function>,
    <function>IsEmpty</function>, <function>Equality</function>,
    <function>Contains</function> and <function>Iterate</function>.
    Some variations on these methods may also be included for various
    optimizations.</para>

    <para>SELECT MANY makes a copy of an instance extent or
    association extent into a transient set variable.  Cursors are
    used to iterate through sets of instances.</para>

    <para>SELECT ANY returns the first element in the instance extent
    or association extent.</para>

    <para>A set generates a different type of variable than does
    an element in a set.  This allows for sets to have attributes
    such as a head (and perhaps a tail and cardinality).  Set
    elements have attributes such as a link to the next element
    and a pointer to the substance of the data they contain.</para>
  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Set Symmetry</title>

    <para>Consistency between the three flavors of collections
    makes the model compiler simpler.  Simpler usually means
    smaller code, but there are some exceptions to this general
    rule.  Up through version 2.2 of &escher;, instance extents,
    association extents and transient sets were treated almost
    identically.  In versions above 2.2, instance extents get
    special treatment so that the model compiler can optimize
    for size and speed based upon characteristics true only of
    instance extents.</para>

    <para>Instance extent sets are treated special in
    that their containers are never returned to the free pool and
    remain permanently attached to the instance data.  Since the
    instances basically move between active (animate) and inactive
    (inanimate) lists, there is no need to detach the container as
    in association extents and transient set variables.  Although
    this breaks the symmetry, it enables the generation of
    smaller and faster code.</para>

    <para>&escher; applies these specializations as
    marking options to enhance the set operation performance
    of the model compiler generated code.</para>
  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Singly Linked Lists</title>

    <para>Singly linked lists are simple and small.  For most of the
    set operations, singly linked lists are fast because of their
    simplicity.  The exception to this is the delete operation.  A
    delete operation on a singly linked set requires the address of
    the container of the data element being deleted.  Delete also
    requires the  address of the container preceding the deleted data
    and the address of the container following the deleted item.  As
    input we have none of these three addresses but only the address
    of the data (object) being deleted.</para>

    <para>In &escher; marked with slist containers, this meant that a
    search for the data element is required.  This search begins at
    the head of the list and proceeds down the list until the data
    element is found.  Variables track the current node and previous
    nodes as the list is traversed.  Once the data element is found,
    these node variables contain 2 of the 3 three needed container
    addresses.  A simple dereference of current->next yields the final
    container address.  The singly linked list delete links the
    previous container to the next container thus unlinking the
    current node.</para>

    <para>As collections get large, this linear search involved
    in set item deletion gets burdensome.</para>

    <figure id="slist-figure" float="1">
    <title id="slist-figure-title">
    Singly Linked Lists of Instances</title>
    <mediaobject><imageobject>
    <imagedata format="&graphicformat;" fileref="slist.&graphicformat;"/>
    </imageobject></mediaobject>
    </figure>

  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Doubly Linked Lists</title>

    <para>Adding a more capable container node structure 
    alleviates the delete instance problem.  With a prev pointer
    together with the next pointer, it is an easy matter to
    learn the address of the previous and following containers
    given the address of the container containing the data to be
    deleted.  Note however, that we are not given the address
    of the container but the address of the data itself.  Thus,
    unless a clever mechanism exists for deriving (divining)
    the container from the data handle, we are relegated to
    linear searches once again.</para>

    <figure id="dlist-figure" float="1">
    <title id="dlist-figure-title">
    Doubly Linked Lists of Instances</title>
    <mediaobject><imageobject>
    <imagedata format="&graphicformat;" fileref="dlist.&graphicformat;"/>
    </imageobject></mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>If data allocation of instances and containers is
    performed in a special way, there does exist a mechanism for
    deriving the address of the container from the address of the
    data.</para>

    <para>In &escher; versions beyond 2.2, a doubly linked list
    container is available.  Instances and containers are
    allocated in memory in a way that relates the instances to
    their containers mathematically.  One container pool is
    allocated for each pool of class instances.  These are
    parallel arrays.  Remember that the container stays
    attached to the instance for the duration of system run
    time, since instances from the extents are simply moved from
    inactive to active and back for create and delete
    respectively.</para>

    <para>During initialization, containers are linked to instance
    data in parallel.  Container 0 is the container for instance
    index 0 of any particular class.  Container 1 is the container
    for the instance at index two in the class pool array for this
    class.  In other words, the array indexes for the containers
    are the same as the array indexes of the instances for which
    they serve.</para>

    <figure id="parallel-figure" float="1">
    <title id="parallel-figure-title">
    Parallel Container/Object Arrays</title>
    <mediaobject><imageobject>
    <imagedata format="&graphicformat;" fileref="parallel.&graphicformat;"/>
    </imageobject></mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Thus, if we know the index of an instance data element,
    we know the index of the instance extent container pointing to
    it.  We can derive the index of any pointer to an array element
    through pointer arithmetic.</para>

    <para>
    <programlisting>
    index = pointer_to_array_element - address_of( array_element[0] )
    </programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>We now have all the information needed to derive the
    address of an instance container, its previous container and
    next container all in constant time.  The delete operation on
    an instance no longer involves a linear search of the
    extent.</para>

    <para>Note that this "magic" only applies to sets managing
    instance extents.  Deletions from association extents,
    UNRELATES, are not helped and still involve a search of the
    set.  UNRELATES from very large association extents (hundreds
    or thousands) can suffer from linear search overhead.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Performance Considerations</title>

    <para>A comparison of the two collection mechanisms in light of
    deleting instances shows the power of the constant time address
    derivation.  Once instance extents grow larger than one
    hundred, the doubly linked collection mechanism with address
    derivation begins to show benefit.  At extent sizes of ten
    thousand (10,000), the singly linked collection mechanism
    becomes two orders of magnitude slower than the doubly linked
    counterpart.</para>
  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Merged Containers</title>

    <para>Another clever way to relate the instance containers to the
    instances themselves is to allocate them
    <emphasis>inside</emphasis> of the instances themselves.  Under
    such a scheme, the base instance class would have the container
    class as its first element.  This would amount to overloading the
    class with container members as data elements, namely next,
    prev, and object.  Such a scheme renders trivial the mathematics
    of deriving the address of the instance from the address of the
    container.  They are exactly the same.  The address of the
    container is the address of the instance (and vice versa).</para>

    <figure id="merged-figure" float="1">
    <title id="merged-figure-title">
    Containers Merged Into Instance Data</title>
    <mediaobject><imageobject>
    <imagedata format="&graphicformat;" fileref="merged.&graphicformat;"/>
    </imageobject></mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Such a scheme suffers a weakness in light of preexisting
    instance (PEI) support.  The merged containers scheme adds two or
    three pointer size data elements to every class instance.  To
    populate the instances with data, it would be necessary to
    populate the container pointers with the instances.  Even if zero,
    this would mean 4 to 12 bytes of additional constant initializer
    data per instance in the system.</para>

    <para>In light of this weakness, &escher; has opted for the
    parallel array approach to mathematically relating the
    containers to the instances.  Even though &escher; does not
    (currently) use merged containers, there remains a great deal
    of merit in the approach.</para>
  </section>
</section>
</chapter>
