<chapter id="Persistence-chapter">
<title id="Persistence-chapter-title">Persistence</title>
<highlights id="Persistence-chapter-high"><para>This chapter describes
persistence services for &escher;.  The persistence support in &escher;
allows instances of classes marked as persistent to survive across
power cycles.</para></highlights>

<section>
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>Persistence capability in a model compiler refers to the ability
  of the model compiler to allow dynamic data to persist across the
  boundary of a power cycle.  The value of a persistent attribute
  written before power disconnect or power loss will be restored when
  the power returns.</para>
  <para>&escher; does not support persistence of dynamic data
  in versions 3.3 and earlier.  This section outlines requirements
  and operation of persistence support.</para>
</section>
  
<section>
  <title>High-Level Requirements</title>
  <section>
    <title>Non-volatile Storage Technology</title>
    <para>There are a great number of options for non-volatile storage
    (NVS) technologies in the embedded control world.  Applications
    exist which use more than one non-volatile storage technology
    within the same system.  It is required that modularity exist
    at the
    interface between general persistence services and the driver
    level code storing and retrieving data from non-volatile storage.
    A bridge is defined to allow &escher; users to build or
    replace this driver layer.</para>
    <para>An option must be supplied to allow for the persisting of the
    current state of a persistent class instance or to use the default
    initial state.  By default &escher; must restore the current state
    of instances.  But the user must have a way of causing the current
    state to be the default current state that would normally be
    established for non-persistent class instances.</para>
  </section>
    
  <section>
    <title>Granularity</title>
    <para>Different applications need to persist different amounts of
    data.  The ability to persist at the class and domain levels
    allows for both large and small amounts of persistent data.
    &escher; supports persistence at class, subsystem and domain levels.
    </para>
  </section>
    
  <section>
    <title>Balance</title>
    <para>Some approaches to persistence can add tremendous complexity
    to the model compiler.  Overly simplistic approaches to
    persistence support can pollute the application analysis.  &escher;
    strikes a balance that makes sense for the embedded
    applications to which &escher; is best suited.</para>
  </section>
</section>
  
<section>
  <title>Operational Overview</title>
  <section>
    <title>General Scenario</title>
    <para>Persistence services for &escher; are light weight and
    flexible in terms of non-volatile storage technology.  The
    persistence services are broken between two domains, PERSIST
    and NVS.</para>
    <para>The PERSIST domain performs the commit and restore
    operations which commit instances to non-volatile storage
    and restore instances from non-volatile storage respectively.
    The PERSIST domain keeps track of which instances have been
    persisted, which links have been persisted and manages keeping
    the links synchronized with the instances during the power-up
    system initialization.</para>
    <para>The NVS domain supplies a rudimentary but functionally
    complete persistent data storage and retrieval interface.
    The interface has characteristics of both a database
    and of a file system.  The interface is rich enough to
    provide flexibility in the application of different non-volatile
    storage technologies.</para>
    <para>&escher; persistence does not specify or depend upon
    a specific persistent storage technology.  Therefore, only
    a standard interface (bridge) is defined.  The user may deploy
    whatever available technology desired behind the bridge to
    the NVS domain.  A sample implementation is supplied (in a file
    called <filename>sys_nvs.c/h</filename>) for use
    as the developer desires.</para>
    <para>The domain chart below shows the bridge operations made
    visible to the application.  <function>commit</function>
    is the primary function used by the application.</para>
    <para>The architecture domain (&escher;) automatically
    performs the <function>insert</function>s, <function>update</function>s
    and <function>delete</function>s to shuffle instance data between the
    RAM based collections of the application and the non-volatile
    persistent storage.  Additionally, &escher; automatically performs the
    <function>restore</function> operation at power-up time.</para>
    <para>Other domain interfaces are exposed and may be
    used at the discretion of the analyst.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Manual and Automatic Commit</title>
    <para>A <emphasis>manual commit</emphasis> occurs when the user
    forces a commit of instance and link data to non-volatile store
    by synchronously invoking a PERSIST domain function (e.g.
    <function>PERSIST::commit()</function>).  An <emphasis>automatic
    commit</emphasis> occurs when a commit is initiated by the software
    architecture "behind the scenes" based on pre-defined policy.</para>
    <para>&escher; supports manual commit operations and performs
    automatic commits when necessary.  Such automatic commits occur
    when instance and link delete operations are required.</para>
    <para>When persistence and tasking are both enabled in the generated
    system, &escher; performs all commits automatically.  It is not advised
    to manually commit in a multi-tasking system.</para>
  </section>
</section>

<section>
  <title>Assumptions</title>
  <para>The implementation and deployment of the Non-Volatile Store (NVS)
  domain is the responsibility of the user.  &escher; supplies one or more
  sample implementations of this domain to serve as design examples and
  source code "head starts".  &mgc; will develop and collect
  additional samples over time and make these available to users.
  However, with the variety of non-volatile storage technologies available
  and broadly differing platform requirements this deployment is left to
  the user for the purposes of flexibility.</para>
  <para>Class instances and relationship instances (links) are stored in
  non-volatile storage.  Their types are kept distinct from the rest of
  their instance data.  In other words, the NVS domain distinguishes
  between instance data and link data.</para>
  <para>Instances and links will be created and deleted in a rigorous 
  fashion in the action language.  Instances will be deleted only after
  all links have been "unrelated".</para>
</section>
  
<section>
  <title>Limitations</title>
  <para>Only class instances and links between
  persistent classes are stored/retrieved from NVS.  (Events and
  timers are not persisted.)</para>
  <para>&escher; instance storage space is reused.  The memory used to
  store the data for a class instance is moved from and to a "pool of
  elements" when creating and deleting class instances.  Thus, after an
  instance is deleted, another instance may be created that uses the
  same physical storage.  This poses a challenge when maintain two
  copies of this data (one in RAM and one in NVS).</para>
  <para>If associations are not unlinked prior to the associated 
  instances being deleted, links will be "orphaned" in non-volatile store.
  As such, this implementation of persistence requires the action
  language to carefully unlink before deleting.</para>
</section>
  
<section>
  <title>Persistence Marking Options</title>
  <para>See <xref linkend="markingpersistence-section"/>
  and <xref linkend="PeristenceCacheDepth-section"/>
  for explanation of the persistence marks.</para>
  <para>A compiler flag exists to change the default behavior of the 
  generated code with regard to restoring the <emphasis>current_state</emphasis>
  of persistence class instances.  To turn off this behavior and
  therefore have the default initial state, compile with
  <command>-DMC3020_DEFAULT_STATE</command>.</para>
</section>
  
<section>
  <title>Analysis</title>

  <figure id="persistdomain-figure" float="0" pgwide="1">
  <title id="persistdomain-figure-title">Persistence Analysis Domain
  Chart</title>
  <mediaobject><imageobject>
  <imagedata format="&graphicformat;" fileref="persistdomain.&graphicformat;"/>
  </imageobject></mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <section>
    <title>Persist Domain Data Analysis</title>
    <para>
    <figure id="persistim-figure" float="0" pgwide="1">
    <title id="persistim-figure-title">Persistence Class Diagram</title>
    <mediaobject><imageobject>
    <imagedata format="&graphicformat;" fileref="persistim.&graphicformat;"/>
    </imageobject></mediaobject>
    </figure>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>PERSIST Domain Functions</title>
    <para>The <function>commit</function> function is called to
    indicate to the domain that the application wants to commit
    instances of classes and associations to non-volatile storage.
    This in turn causes <function>NVS::insert</function> to be called
    flushing to NVS elements from a list of instances and links that
    were queued when modified.</para>
    <para>A return value of 0 indicates success.</para>
    <funcsynopsis>
    <funcprototype>
    <funcdef>integer <function>commit</function></funcdef>
    <void/>
    </funcprototype>
    </funcsynopsis>
    <para>The <function>restore</function> function is called by the
    architecture during bring-up after a power cycle.  The
    <function>restore</function> function causes the classes contained
    in non-volatile storage to be read from store and written to the
    instance collection list.</para>
    <para>A return value of 0 indicates success.</para>
    <funcsynopsis>
    <funcprototype>
    <funcdef>integer <function>restore</function></funcdef>
    <paramdef>integer <parameter>class</parameter></paramdef>
    </funcprototype>
    </funcsynopsis>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Non-volatile Storage Domain Data Analysis</title>
    <para>
    <figure id="nvsim-figure" float="0" pgwide="1">
    <title id="nvsim-figure-title">Non-Volatile Storage Class Diagram</title>
    <mediaobject><imageobject>
    <imagedata format="&graphicformat;" fileref="nvsim.&graphicformat;"/>
    </imageobject></mediaobject>
    </figure>
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Non-volatile Storage Domain Functions</title>
    <para>Many NVS domain functions return an integer return code.  The
    values that the return code can take are outlined in the following
    listing:
    <programlisting>
#define NVS_RETURN_SUCCESS    0 /* All is well.                    */
#define NVS_ERROR_BAD_OPEN   -1 /* Could not open file.            */
#define NVS_ERROR_ITEM_LONG  -2 /* Data item is too long.          */
#define NVS_ERROR_BAD_SEEK   -3 /* Could not seek correctly.       */
#define NVS_ERROR_BAD_WRITE  -4 /* File did not write correctly.   */
#define NVS_ERROR_NOT_FOUND  -5 /* Did not find searched record.   */
#define NVS_ERROR_BAD_READ   -6 /* Read incorrect length of data.  */
#define NVS_ERROR_NO_ROOM    -7 /* Not enough room for insert.     */
#define NVS_ERROR_LENGTH     -8 /* Length not correct.             */
    </programlisting>
    This can be found in the generated
    <filename>NVS_bridge.h</filename> file.  A positive value is used
    to indicate the length of a buffer.</para>
    <para>Function <function>checksum</function> provides a
    mathematical redundancy check on the integrity of the contents of
    the non-volatile store (NVS).  This mathematical algorithm and the
    capabilities of the function are supplied by the implementor of the
    internals of the NVS module.</para>
    <para><function>checksum</function> provides an integer return code
    representing an integrity check on the contents of the NVS.</para>
    <funcsynopsis>
    <funcprototype>
    <funcdef>integer <function>checksum</function></funcdef>
    <paramdef>integer <parameter>first</parameter></paramdef>
    <paramdef>integer <parameter>second</parameter></paramdef>
    </funcprototype>
    </funcsynopsis>
    <para>The <function>defrag</function> function coalesces deleted
    records together and written records together.  This allows for
    small fragments of free storage to be collected into a single
    contiguous free piece of storage.  This function will typically
    take significant time to run.  This time is a function of the
    specific non-volatile storage technology.</para>
    <para><function>defrag</function> provides an integer return
    code as listed above.</para>
    <funcsynopsis>
    <funcprototype>
    <funcdef>integer <function>defrag</function></funcdef>
    <void/>
    </funcprototype>
    </funcsynopsis>
    <para><function>delete</function> searches the store for an item
    matching the input and deletes it.  Deleted items cannot be
    retrieved from NVS in future invocations of <function>select</function>
    or <function>search</function>.  <function>delete</function>
    chooses the item to erase based on two combinations of input
    arguments.  If the <function>delete</function> is called with a key
    and a type, then the item in the NVS matching these key and type
    arguments is erased.  Otherwise, if non-null data is given, the data
    and type arguments are used to identify the item to delete.  When
    found, the item is marked as deleted and will not be readable from
    the store.</para>
    <para><function>delete</function> provides an integer return code
    as listed above.</para>
    <funcsynopsis>
    <funcprototype>
    <funcdef>integer <function>delete</function></funcdef>
    <paramdef>integer <parameter>key</parameter></paramdef>
    <paramdef>integer <parameter>length</parameter></paramdef>
    <paramdef>string <parameter>pointer</parameter></paramdef>
    <paramdef>integer <parameter>type</parameter></paramdef>
    </funcprototype>
    </funcsynopsis>
    <para>The <function>format</function> function erases the
    non-volatile store (NVS).  It is only to be called when it is
    desired that a new NVS be cleared and prepared for writing for the
    first time.</para>
    <funcsynopsis>
    <funcprototype>
    <funcdef>integer <function>format</function></funcdef>
    <void/>
    </funcprototype>
    </funcsynopsis>
    <para>The <function>initialize</function> function resets the
    internal counters of the non-volatile store.  (Note that these
    internal counters are the responsibility of the implementor of the
    internal of NVS and can contain information about the amount of
    data being used, etc.)  No application/user data is written or
    changed in the store.  This function is called automatically at
    power-up to prepare the store for access.</para>
    <para><function>initialize</function> provides an integer return
    code as listed above.</para>
    <funcsynopsis>
    <funcprototype>
    <funcdef>integer <function>initialize</function></funcdef>
    <void/>
    </funcprototype>
    </funcsynopsis>
    <para>The <function>insert</function> function adds items to the
    store.  There are four input arguments.  The first,
    <emphasis>key</emphasis> is the lookup key to the item.  In the
    case of instance data, this key is a unique identifier for the item
    being inserted (added to the store).  <emphasis>length</emphasis>
    is an integer representation of the length of the data byte
    sequence pointed to by pointer.  <emphasis>type</emphasis> is the
    class type (instance or link) in integer form.  The data pointed to
    by <emphasis>pointer</emphasis> is not modified.  If the record
    being inserted already exists in the non-volatile store, the
    existing record will be updated.  A return code provides status on
    the insert.</para>
    <funcsynopsis>
    <funcprototype>
    <funcdef>integer <function>insert</function></funcdef>
    <paramdef>integer <parameter>key</parameter></paramdef>
    <paramdef>integer <parameter>length</parameter></paramdef>
    <paramdef>string <parameter>pointer</parameter></paramdef>
    <paramdef>integer <parameter>type</parameter></paramdef>
    </funcprototype>
    </funcsynopsis>
    <para><function>next</function> provides a way to cycle through
    reading each item from the store one at a time.  This
    function returns the item currently being pointed to by the cursor
    (maintained inside the store).  The buffer space available on the
    calling side is passed in as the length argument.  If sufficient
    space is available in the buffer, the next item data will be copied
    into the given buffer pointed to by pointer.  The length of the
    written data is returned as the return value.  Also returned are
    the values of the key and type.  The initialize function resets the
    internal cursor to the first item in the store.</para>
    <funcsynopsis>
    <funcprototype>
    <funcdef>integer <function>next</function></funcdef>
    <paramdef>integer * <parameter>key</parameter></paramdef>
    <paramdef>integer <parameter>length</parameter></paramdef>
    <paramdef>integer * <parameter>pointer</parameter></paramdef>
    <paramdef>integer * <parameter>type</parameter></paramdef>
    </funcprototype>
    </funcsynopsis>
    <para>The <function>select</function> function searches the store
    for a specific item with a key and type matching those given as
    input arguments.  If a record is found that matches, it is copied
    into the data buffer pointed to by pointer.  The length argument
    provides the amount of buffer space available on the calling side.
    The actual length of the returned record (if one is returned) is
    provided in the return value.  The data behind the pointer argument
    is modified with the data found in the non-volatile store.</para>
    <funcsynopsis>
    <funcprototype>
    <funcdef>integer <function>select</function></funcdef>
    <paramdef>integer <parameter>key</parameter></paramdef>
    <paramdef>integer <parameter>length</parameter></paramdef>
    <paramdef>string * <parameter>pointer</parameter></paramdef>
    <paramdef>integer <parameter>type</parameter></paramdef>
    </funcprototype>
    </funcsynopsis>
    <para>The <function>space_available</function> function returns an
    integer representing the number of bytes not being used in the
    store.  This number of bytes will actually hold fewer bytes due to
    the overhead of item meta-data (key, type, etc).</para>
    <funcsynopsis>
    <funcprototype>
    <funcdef>integer <function>space_available</function></funcdef>
    <void/>
    </funcprototype>
    </funcsynopsis>
    <para>The <function>space_total</function> function returns the
    overall size in bytes of the non-volatile store.</para>
    <funcsynopsis>
    <funcprototype>
    <funcdef>integer <function>space_total</function></funcdef>
    <void/>
    </funcprototype>
    </funcsynopsis>
    <para>The <function>space_used</function> function returns the
    number of bytes currently written in the store.</para>
    <funcsynopsis>
    <funcprototype>
    <funcdef>integer <function>space_used</function></funcdef>
    <void/>
    </funcprototype>
    </funcsynopsis>
    <para>The <function>update</function> function searches for a
    record in the store the same way that <function>select</function>
    does.  When (and if) a record is found, the new data of length
    length pointed to by pointer is written into the store over the
    existing item.  Since <function>insert</function> will perform an
    update when a record exists, it is more often used than
    <function>update</function>.  No arguments are modified calling
    this function.</para>
    <para><function>update</function> provides an integer return code
    as listed above.</para>
    <funcsynopsis>
    <funcprototype>
    <funcdef>integer <function>update</function></funcdef>
    <paramdef>integer <parameter>key</parameter></paramdef>
    <paramdef>integer <parameter>length</parameter></paramdef>
    <paramdef>string <parameter>pointer</parameter></paramdef>
    <paramdef>integer <parameter>type</parameter></paramdef>
    </funcprototype>
    </funcsynopsis>
    <para>Function <function>version</function> provides an integer
    return value indicating the version of the data and/or format
    of the non-volatile store (NVS).
    This versioning algorithm and the
    capabilities of the function are supplied by the implementor of the
    internals of the NVS module.  Two input arguments are used to
    provide flexible utility.</para>
    <para><function>version</function> provides an integer return code
    representing the version of the NVS (contents).</para>
    <funcsynopsis>
    <funcprototype>
    <funcdef>integer <function>version</function></funcdef>
    <paramdef>integer <parameter>first</parameter></paramdef>
    <paramdef>integer <parameter>second</parameter></paramdef>
    </funcprototype>
    </funcsynopsis>
  </section>

</section>

<section id="persistimplementation-section">
<title id="persistimplementation-section-title">Persistence Design</title>

  <section>
    <title>Class-Based Create/Delete/Init</title>

    <para>Primary infrastructure changes involve the centralization
    of the create, delete and initialization of class instances.  The
    following paragraphs explain this change and its
    design.  A description of the implementation of the generated code
    follows with an explanation of the effects on speed, space and
    execution.</para>

    <para>&escher; 3.3 and before has a class-based create, delete, init
    design.  The generated code contains a create accessor, delete
    accessor and factory initializer for each class in the modeled
    system.  When an instance needs to be created, a routine specific
    to the class is invoked to allocate the implementation memory for
    the class instance.  The attributes for the class instance are
    given reasonable default initial values.  Identifying attributes of
    type unique_id are initialized to values certain to be unique with
    the generated system.  The initial state of the new instance state
    machine is set.</para>

    <para>In &escher; 3.3 and before, when an instance needs to be
    deleted, a routine specific to the class is called to deallocate
    the implementation memory for the instance and perform needed
    clean-up.</para>

    <para>&escher; 3.3 generates "object factory initialization"
    routines.  There is one of these methods for each class in the
    modeled domains.  These methods are called exactly once at bring-up
    time to initialize the instance memory data pool for the collection
    of instances for the class.  This routine took into consideration
    the fact that some of the instances in a collection may be
    allocated and initialized statically as preexisting instances.
    </para>

    <para>The class-based create/delete/init approach is very flexible.
    It allows the model compiler designer the liberty of considering
    only the class in hand when generating the code.  Different
    profiles of deployment code can be generated based upon the type of
    class (passive, active, associative, having preexisting instances,
    etc).  However, having the create, delete and init accessor
    dispersed to every class is troublesome when considering a
    persistent restore operation from centralized non-volatile storage
    (NVS).</para>
  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Centralized Create/Delete/Init</title>

    <para>&escher; 3.4 and beyond centralizes the create, delete and
    initialize operations.  This is accomplished by moving the
    intelligence of the class-based create/delete/init procedures into
    a class-based data structure.  This class_info array contains
    information about each class such that centralized operations can
    intelligently create, delete and initialize classes and
    instances.</para>

    <para>The information contained in the class_info structure includes:
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry><term>active</term><listitem><para>The head of the
      list of active instances is used to collect the active instances
      together.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>inactive</term><listitem><para>The head of
      the list of inactive instances is also maintained and used during
      create and delete operations.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>container</term><listitem><para>Container
      refers to the head of the list of container elements used to
      maintain collections.  The base of this list is used to calculate
      indexes into the array of
      instances.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>pool</term><listitem><para>The base of the
      array representing the pool of instance data is accessible from
      the class_info array.  The base of this list also is used to
      calculate indexes into the array of
      instances.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>size</term><listitem><para>The size of the
      class (in bytes) is necessary for initialization and for
      persistence support.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>initial_state</term><listitem><para>For
      active classes, the starting state of state machines must be kept
      for initialization of newly created active
      instances.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>population</term><listitem><para>Population
      is the number of instances in the instance
      collection.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry><term>[preexisting
      instances]</term><listitem><para>Is used when there are
      preexisting instances defined in data.  This element will inform
      the global initialization routine how many active instances to
      expect at power up so that initialization of collections may
      proceed accordingly.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    With the above information, it is possible to have centrally
    defined create, delete and initialization routines.  These central
    routines rely on class-specific information from the class_info
    array rather than on class-specific generated procedures.</para>
  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Implications to Persistence Support</title>

    <para>The persistence restore operation relies heavily upon the
    centralized create and initialization routines.  Assuming for a
    moment a system that has no preexisting instances defined in data,
    a system having persistent classes must restore the class instance
    data from a central non-volatile storage unit (NVS).</para>

    <para>When a system powers up, it performs the standard system
    level initialization to bring up event queues and timer support and
    other system level infrastructure.  The system then initializes the
    collection mechanisms for all of the classes in the generated
    system.  This involves linking the instance storage into lists
    (singly or doubly linked).</para>

    <para>At this point in a non-persistence supporting system the
    initialization functions would be invoked to allow application
    level user initialization to occur.  In a persistence supporting
    system, persistent class instances are restored from
    non-volatile storage before the user initialization functions are
    run.</para>

    <para>The process of restoring class instances involves invoking
    the central create routine and populating the newly created
    instance with data from NVS.  The data in the NVS needs to be rich
    enough such that the create routine knows which type of class to
    create.  Once the type is communicated, the class_info array
    provides the necessary details to enable the correct instantiation
    of the new instance.</para>
  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Implementation</title>

    <para>In &escher; 3.3 the files <filename>*_object.c</filename>
    contain methods to create, delete and perform factory
    initialization of class instances.  To compare implementations,
    view one of these files in 3.3 generated code.</para>

    <para>In &escher; 3.4 and beyond, these routines are centralized.
    The class_info structure is
    simply an array of pointers to elements of the structure which
    reside in the individual <filename>*_class.c</filename>
    files.</para>

    <para>Each domain is assigned a unique number, and each class
    within a domain is assigned a unique number.  An array of
    class_info arrays exists for the system containing information for
    all classes in all domains.  During translation a domain-unique number
    is assigned to each class.  This number serves as an index into the
    class_info array thus allowing centralized create, delete, init and
    other routines to look up statistics on any class in the
    modeled system.</para>
  </section>


  <section>
    <title>Effects</title>

    <para>Centralizing the create, delete and init functions has the
    intended effect of enabling a persistent restore operation that can
    rely on these class-independent routines (namely create).  There
    are positive side-effects of this centralization.</para>

    <para>Code space savings is the primary positive side effect.
    Instead of three routines for each class, there are now three
    routines for the entire system.  This saves substantially on code
    size in the generated system.  This effect will be greatest on
    systems with a large number of classes.</para>

    <para>Other positive side effects include greater flexibility in
    features such as persistence.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Cost Modeling</title>
    <para>Persistence services have cost in terms of execution speed,
    instruction store space, data memory and non-volatile storage
    space.  This section enumerates those costs in as detailed a manner
    as practical.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Data Memory Cost</title>
      <para>To manage the bookkeeping of persistent instances,
      additional data is maintained.  The following additional
      storage is used for each instance of each class.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem><para>The <emphasis>instance index</emphasis> is kept
        for each instance (all instances in the system).  This value
        represents the index into the array of instances.  The value is
        the index of the class instance when it was stored into NVS.
        This is required during the restore operation.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>The <emphasis>class number</emphasis> is required
        inside the non-volatile store.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>list of pointers to link functions
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>list of class numbers
        </para></listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Instruction Store (Code Space) Cost</title>
      <para>NVS domain:  approximated 3000 bytes (on 32 bit Intel)</para>
      <para>PERSIST domain:  approximated 4000 bytes (on 32 bit Intel)</para>
      <para>There is significant cost in queueing the modified instances
      to the NVS cache queue.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Cost in Speed</title>
      <para>The cost in speed is largely driven by the speed of
      the non-volatile store technology.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Non-volatile Memory Cost</title>
      <para>An instance in NVS is identical in size to an instance in RAM.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

</section>
    
</chapter>
