<title id="taskingapi-title">
Interfacing Generated Code with Outside Tasks
</title>
<highlights id="taskingapi-high"><para>
</para></highlights>

    
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>BridgePoint xtUML models compiled with MC-3020 can be
    interfaced with non-modeled code in a number of ways.  All
    interfacing with external code (modeled or non-modeled) is performed
    through call-return interfaces.  Models can call code; code can call
    models.  Models call non-modeled code through bridge operations.
    Non-modeled code calls models by invoking the domain functions
    defined in the model.  "User call-outs" supply another mechanism to
    interface models with non-modeled code.  Lastly, any code can call
    the "main" function entry point of the modeled system.
    </para>

    <para>Out-of-the-box MC-3020 supports multi-tasking/threading by
    enabling this feature with the appropriate markings (EnableTasking,
    SetTaskPriority and MapClassToTask).  The default behavior is limited
    to tasking/threading within a single address space.  The C code
    generated from models with MC-3020 runs in a single process with no
    modification.  Integrating the generated code with code running in
    separate (independent memory space) tasks requires additional work
    by the user.  This report explains how this integration can occur.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Assumptions</title>
    <para>These sections assume some familiarity with BridgePoint and
    MC-3020.  Sections in the MC-3020 User's Guide on Tasking, Bridging,
    Interrupt Service Routines (ISRs) and Interface Call-outs are
    especially applicable.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Interrupt Service Routines</title>
    <para>MC-3020 generated code is often run in applications with
    interrupt service routines activated by hardware, timers and other
    input stimuli.  These interrupt service routines preempt lower
    priority contexts and run in a context separate from the main
    application.
    </para>
    <para>Interrupt service routines can call domain functions in exactly
    the same way that other non-modeled code calls domain functions.  It
    is good design in most cases to minimize the amount of time spent
    running in an interrupt service routine.  The routine will want to
    note the source of the interrupt, report it to the main application
    and drop off (release the context) as quickly as possible.  In
    modeled applications this usually takes the shape of an invocation to
    a domain function that simply generates an event.
    </para>
    <para>Since interrupt service routines preempt other executing
    contexts, special care must be taken to avoid interference with data
    elements shared between contexts.  Without taking care, an interrupt
    service routine can read or write data that is in an incomplete or
    unknown state.
    </para>
    <para>MC-3020 provides a means of handling high priority
    interrupt-level invocations of domain functions while maintaining
    safe and consistent data access.  This is done by marking a domain
    function as "safe" for interrupt invocation.  To indicate to the
    model compiler that a domain function is to be called by interrupt
    service routines, invoke marking function
    TagSyncServiceSafeForInterrupts.
    </para>
    <para>See "Marking a Bridge Safe for Interrupt Invocation" in the
    MC-3020 User's Guide.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Task Interfaces</title>
    <para>The tasking interfaces described here refer to full,
    "heavy-weight" tasks (or processes) that run in their own virtual
    address spaces.  As stated above BridgePoint with MC-3020 supports
    "light-weight" tasking, threads running in a shared address space.
    However, MC-3020 provides no specific native interfacing for
    heavy-weight tasking.  Applications running in separate processes
    must use the inter-process communication facilities of the underlying
    operating system (e.g. signals and signal handlers).
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Bridging Through Domain Functions</title>
      <para>The simplest tasking interface follows the same pattern as
      the interrupt handler interface.  Instead of an interrupt handler,
      there will be a signal handler.  Upon being signaled or messaged,
      the handler will invoke a domain function.  Similarly to the
      ISR-invoked domain function, the domain function that is invoked
      from the signal handler often simply generates an event.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Allowing the Process to Suspend</title>
      <para>Default MC-3020 tasking support allows the BridgePoint
      modeled application to suspend (go non-busy) when the event queues
      are empty.  By enabling tasking (threading) with the marking
      functions, this behavior is enabled.  If tasking/threading is not
      enabled, the background idle loop of the application will simply
      spin.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Resuming the Process</title>
      <para>A modeled application that has no events in its event queues
      will suspend.  To wake the application up, an xtUML event must be
      generated to some state machine within the application.  This is
      the job of the domain function invocation described above.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Restarting from Initialization</title>
      <para>Another method of interfacing MC-3020 generated code with other
      code is by invoking the beginning of the program each time the user
      wants the modeled application to run.  This starts the modeled
      application over from the beginning at each invocation.
      </para>
      <para>This method has the advantage of simplicity but the
      disadvantage of unnecessary re-initialization on every invocation.
      This method is dependent upon clean exit of the tasks/threads between
      invocations.  This means that the operating system must have time to
      allow the process to complete, exit and relinquish resources before
      being invoked again.  In a single-threaded environment this is not an
      issue.
      </para>
      <section>
        <title>Steps to Invocation</title>
        <para>Using this method of integration the user follows the steps
        listed below.
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem><para>Rename the main using the marking file
          sys_functions.arc.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Invoke the newly named main by forking/spawning
          a task with this entry point.  </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Allow the task to exit and clean up.
          </para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Repeat steps 2 and 3 as often as the modeled
          task is desired to run.  </para></listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
