<chapter id="Tasking-chapter">
<title id="Tasking-chapter-title">Tasking/Threading</title>
<highlights id="Tasking-chapter-high"><para>&escher; supports running
the xtUML application within multiple tasks or threads.  The tasking
uses the underlying OS/RTOS when one exists.  &escher; can still run
without an OS/RTOS, but if preemptive multi-tasking is desired in
the application, it is available.  The tasking/threading
capabilities for &escher; are outlined here.</para></highlights>

<section>
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>A well-modeled xtUML application is inherently concurrent.
  Actions from any two or more instances are considered to run
  simultaneously.  This concurrency at the specification level
  simplifies the task of the developer.  Smaller bits of system can be
  modeled to run somewhat independently.  The life-cycles of classes in
  a system can be modeled mostly independently considering only their
  synchronization with other classes in the system.  For example, the
  microwave door and the turntable run concurrently and mostly without
  recognizing or caring that the other exists or is running.  If
  Developer A is modeling the door, and Developer B is modeling the
  turntable, they can do their state modeling with loose
  coupling.</para>
  <para>To begin using the tasking/threading capability right away,
  jump to <xref linkend="Tasking-Marking-section"/>.</para>
  <para>A form of the inherent concurrency of the xtUML model can
  easily be translated and realized in a single-tasking microcontroller
  target.  In single-tasking mode, &escher; interleaves the state
  actions of multiple concurrent instances of executing classes.</para>
  <para>A single-tasking deployment architecture achieves a level of
  concurrency in which state actions from actively running class
  instances are interleaved.  Such a deployment design serves well
  for applications requiring concurrency at the granularity of a
  state action.  It is light weight and fast.</para>
  <para>However, if a finer grained concurrency is desired, it will be
  necessary to use a multi-tasking deployment system.  In a
  multi-tasking deployment environment, state actions can run in
  concurrently executing tasks or threads.  The number of currently
  executing actions can be equal to the number of executing tasks
  (instead of just one).</para>
</section>

<section id="Tasking-Marking-section">
  <title id="Tasking-Marking-section-title">Marking for Tasking</title>
  <para>To use tasking/threading with &escher;, the user must mark the
  feature enabled providing the "flavor" of tasking/threading provided
  by the underlying operating system (OS) or real-time operating system
  (RTOS).  Use the marking described <xref
  linkend="Marking-EnablingTasking-section"/>.</para>
  <para>Once the tasking/threading capability has been enabled, the
  priorities of the desired tasks must be established.  Various
  operating systems (OSes) and real-time operating systems (RTOSes) use
  different symbology for setting priority.  For example, &nukeplus;
  uses integer numbers between 0 and 255 to indicate the priority of a
  task.  (0 is the highest priority; 255 is the lowest.) Use the
  marking function described in <xref
  linkend="Marking-TaskPriority-section"/> to set the priority of the
  tasks in the xtUML generated system.</para>
  <para>Classes must be mapped to the tasks identified with the marking
  functions above.  Use the marking function described in <xref
  linkend="Marking-MappingClassesToTasks-section"/> to map classes to
  tasks.</para>
</section>
  
<section id="Tasking-Prioritization-section">
  <title id="Tasking-Prioritization-section-title">Prioritization</title>

  <para>The primary reason for tasking in an xtUML modeled system
  involves the deployment of prioritization in the generated code.</para>

  <section id="Tasking-PriorityGeneration-section">
    <title id="Tasking-PriorityGeneration-section-title">Priority in the
    Generated Code</title>
    <para>An xtUML model may be inherently concurrent, but it is not
    inherently prioritized.</para>
    <para>Simple prioritization of execution of a
    translated xtUML model can be achieved without multi-tasking.
    Events can be prioritized to modify the sequencing of state
    actions.  &escher; provides event prioritization.</para>
    <para>In a single tasking environment, a state action cannot be
    preempted.  Therefore, a single task deployment environment is
    limited by the duration of the longest state action.  Without
    preemption, a higher priority action may need to wait the entire
    duration of a state action of lower priority processing.  Sometimes
    this is not an issue.</para>
    <para>However, in many embedded applications the limits of a single
    task cannot be tolerated.  We must map the xtUML application onto a
    multi-tasking/multi-threading architecture.  By doing so, it is
    possible to map processing to various tasks based upon the required
    priorities.  Higher priority action processing can be designed to
    preempt lower priority actions.  We can take control away from the
    lower priority action and context switch into the higher priority
    action running in a higher priority task.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="Tasking-Mapping-section">
    <title id="Tasking-Mapping-section-title">Mapping to Tasks</title>
    <para>There are many possible strategies for mapping the components
    of an xtUML application to tasks.  Event-based strategies and
    strategies based upon sequences of actions have been implemented
    successfully.  &escher; has supported event based prioritization
    since version 2.  As of &escher; version 4, prioritization using
    tasks/threads is supported.  The mapping of xtUML artifacts to
    these tasks/threads is by class.  Groups of classes are mapped to
    the tasks/threads running in the generated system.</para>
    <para>xtUML model marking is used to identify which classes are
    translated to run in which tasks in the deployment target.  Each
    class is marked identifying the task in which its generated code
    runs.  The priority of the action processing of the class is used
    to determine an appropriate task.  Higher priority classes get
    mapped to higher priority tasks.  This separation allows for the
    processing of higher priority classes to preempt the processesing
    of lower priority classes.</para>
    <para>Classes with state charts requiring low latency response to
    application events are mapped to high priority.  Classes with
    little or no requirement for quick response are mapped to lower
    priority RTOS tasks.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How Many Tasks?</title>
    <para>The number of tasks required by the application is largely
    driven by prioritization.  Concurrency plays a part in
    determining the number of tasks needed.  The mapping to
    tasks must be accomplished with a clear understanding of both the
    xtUML application and of the deployment target hardware and
    RTOS.</para>
    <para>A simple starting point is to have one task for each
    required level of priority.  Map all classes having the same
    priority to the same task.  For example map classes with tight
    coupling to time sensitive hardware to high priority task(s).
    Map classes that do non-critical "background" types of processing
    to a low priority task.  Map everything else to a normal priority
    task.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Data Access Issues</title>
    <para>In an xtUML application concurrency is assumed unless
    purposefully sequenced.  Access to data that is shared between
    various classes/actions/functions must be synchronized.  A
    simple, single-tasking deployment target may hide synchronization
    issues.  A multi-tasking environment will not hide these modeling
    defects and indeed may aggravate them.  If an xtUML application
    has not been properly synchronized, a truly preemptive
    multi-tasking kernel can uncover the modeling deficiencies.</para>
    <para>Note that it is wise to map classes with strong processing
    and data interaction (coupling) into the same task.  An improper
    mapping of classes to tasks can increase the overhead of
    processing by introducing undue task switching.</para>
  </section>
</section>

<section id="Tasking-Deployment-section">
  <title>Tasking/Threading in the Generated Code</title>
  <para>&escher; interfaces to the tasking/threading capabilities of
  the underlying OS/RTOS through a single interface layer module.
  The interface module is generated into the generated source of the 
  system node into a file called <filename>sys_thread.c</filename>.</para>
  <para>The tasking/threading interface consists of six interfaces.
  One interface provides for initialization
  (<function>InitializeThreading</function>).  Another interface
  provides for creating threads
  (<function>thread_create</function>).  Two interfaces allow
  for the locking and unlocking of shared resources such as event
  and instance queues (<function>mutex_lock/unlock</function>).
  Two final interfaces allow for the class activities in a task to go
  "non-busy" using no cycles when there is no work to do
  (<function>nonbusy_wait/wake</function>) and to "wake up" when new
  work arrives.</para>
  <para>The resources that are protected by the locking and unlocking
  interfaces include instance event queue, self event queue, collection
  element free list, non-busy lock, serialization lock, instance
  queues, timers and interleaved bridges.</para>
</section>
    
</chapter>
